this is instead of the usual trend of
people attacking each other's belief
systems I think this is a really
important question and it has a kind of
an extensive answer I'll concentrate
more on the second part of the answer
which is the recommendation for wisdom
practices I think a lot of the perennial
problems can be found within ideological
systems both within the individuals
partaking or participating in those
ideologies and with the the way sort of
groups are also organized around
ideologies the main thing I think the
the the main kind of risk that I see
ideologies going for is an attempt for a
kind of cognitive closure a kind of
completeness as many people have pointed
out this is not an idea original to me
there's a totalizing aspect to
ideologies and I think not only does
that of course trap us within
propositional thinking and disconnect us
from procedural perspectival and
participatory and I've argued at length
why I think that's the case and why it's
profound I think the way in which
ideologies push for this totalization
and closure puts them fundamentally at
odds with both the machinery of
relevance realization as something that
is ongoing and evolving and if you'll
allow me a metaphor the machinery of
reality which is ultimately
inexhaustible and dynamically unfolding
and so I think the risk for the risk of
sort of specific to ideologies is
exactly the way in which they
prematurely and permanently try to
inappropriately collapse the complexity
combine the complexity of reality and of
our cognition combined it so we all need
to do that we have to at times compress
and collapse the complexity but when
then that is coupled to claims of
certainty and that therefore justify
actions undertaken in the name of that
audiology that's particularly where all
of this becomes deeply deeply dangerous
and when when that happens all of our
paradigmatic propositions and pictures
that we use to try and clarify things
for ourselves actually start to blind us
in a powerful way so the whole thing
becomes a a kind of self-deception in
the thing that is supposed to provide a
framing lens for us actually become
something opaquely blinding and we're
looking at it rather than looking
through it and so in that in that way of
thinking I want to use a biblical term
to describe what I think the most
besetting problem is a risk for ideal
ideologies and it's a nice one because
it's mnemonic and that's idolatry
so idolatry is when we forget not just
in assertion but if forget in our
existential mode how much our cognition
and how much reality transcend our
egocentric grasp and that we can lose
our connection of allow me some
Tillich's terms some atelic strim to
what is ultimate when we forget that and
we take our belief systems to be
complete consistent and finished and of
course you can even here go deleon
reasons why that's ultimately a failed
project we have to find better ways of
addressing the existential anxieties
that people attempt to alleviate
through ideologies and so what I'm
proposing is we need two kinds of wisdom
practices that will help address this
tendency towards closure perfectionism
certainty idolatry of ideologies we need
ones that make us capable of dealing
with incompleteness dealing with
imperfection and still valuing the
connections that are being formed within
cognitive processes that cannot bring a
certainty cannot bring this completeness
cannot bring this finality stop
pretending that it might get made me a
bit a little little harsher but stop
pretending that we have achieved these
and so one set of practices would be
needed in order to make people more
comfortable dealing with the existential
anxieties that are often triggered by
ambiguity uncertainty and there is a
whole host of practices around this many
of them have to do with helping to train
people in mindfulness to step back and
look at their processing rather than
automatically looking through it
cognitive reframing things of course
people also have to do their own
particular psychodynamic work and
whatever practices will help address
that to alleviate their idiosyncratic
causes of anxiety so you're going to
need a set of practices for reducing
anxiety then I would say you need a set
of practices that get people more
familiar with a flowing thought the flow
state in particular that flowing kind of
coupled miss to reality in which the
what makes the experience so wonderful
is not any sense of it being fixed and
complete and closed but per but instead
exactly the opposite the flow state is
so wondrous to people for us because it
takes them to the edge of awe it takes
them to the sense of ongoing opening
ongoing discovery so this of course
leads
the general point which is the set of
wisdom practices that are needed are
ones that are going to achieve some kind
of reciprocal opening and an agog a so
you have anxiety reduction practices you
have an agogic practices and then the
third kind of practice you want to bring
in is the one I'm doing a lot of work on
right now especially with Christopher
master Pietro and Peter Lindbergh and
then all the excellent discussions I've
having with guys in stock and Jordan
Hall and also with Andrew Sweeney this
is the the set of practices that I call
dialectic that are designed to engender
deea logos these are practices in which
we try to bring into our dialoguing with
other that feature of reciprocal opening
and we try to reorient towards the
what's our what we're valuing we're
valuing our ability to connect to each
other ourselves and reality and to
evolve our meaning making machinery and
so what's interesting is Peter and I are
exploring the idea of a lot of these
emerging biological practices and I will
go into this in great length when I when
I'm in the series after Socrates but we
need practices and one practice that
might do this is Ivan Russia's practice
on empathy circling because what it's
designed to do is bring people from bad
faith to good faith dialog there's a
practice I've been talking with another
patron about that social noting which is
a sort of group mindfulness practice
that gets people into a kind of sink
there's various other practices that you
do sort of warming up for circling that
shift people into getting the conditions
right for a collective flow state within
collective intelligence and then once
that circling kind of practice is
flowing what it what you can then do is
think about there's a lot here so but
you can think about a way in which
you're getting
resonance in which you're moving between
immersion in the practice in which you
are exemplifying meaning making and
perhaps exemplifying reciprocal opening
and exemplifying wisdom and then
stepping back and noting it explicate
drawing that out and then bringing in
sort of philosophical questionings not
as abstract theorizing but it's
something that is going to be woven into
the flowing texture of the conversation
the question might be well what is
meaning what is wisdom what is it
to love someone else and to bring that
into the dialogue and I think if we
shifted to these dialogical processes we
could do the most important shift which
is indicative of rationality so what I'm
proposing is let's try to bring into our
collective processes one of the key
things that is a marker of rationality
and individuals one of the key things
that Marxist rationality individuals is
a shift off the fixation on the product
and the position that you're taking and
shift on to participation in a process
and that if we could that that what I'm
suggesting that is what we need to
figure out how to bring into our
collective distributed cognition ability
to as groups shift off product and
position and shift into participation in
process because what we need is not
another ideology we've had that we've
tried that we keep trying it right
instead what we need is a reconnection
with the lifeblood of wisdom and meaning
making that is what we need and we can
do that we can we weave collective
intelligence and we can spin it into
collective rationality and together we
can aspire to collective wisdom because
that's what we need to solve our
problems so thank you Daniel
very extensive sorry at that very
important question and I hope my
somewhat extensive answer at least is
good grounds for thought and further
discussion between us the next question
is from the patron McKenzie Levitt it's
always good to get questions from
McKenzie always appreciated the question
is for you personally on your own
journey how would you describe the most
important insight you've ever had who
that's that's a rough one in terms of
trying to sort of decide I guess the one
I would pick because it's sort of a
route insight to a bunch of other things
was one I had so a little bit about
autobiographic set up the context so I
finished my PhD and I sort of zeroed in
on this problem of relevance and how
crucial it is and I'd done some work
with my very good friend and she happy
but difficulties about trying to
generate scientific theories of
relevance and I had become quite sort of
depressed part of it was I was done my
PhD and whenever you're done your PhD
you just go into a depression but the
other the other aspect of it was for
reasons that I take a lot of time to
articulate in the series and so I hope
I'm not being presumptuous now I think
of relevance realization is just
fundamentally central to our cognitive
agency to our meaning-making to our
meaning in life to our experience of
religio or experience of the sacredness
and this had all become clear to me and
then it was like well I'd seem to got to
a place where there's no there's no
explanation for this there's no
scientific explanation even possible for
this for some of the reasons I actually
cover in this series and that was
a really sort of weird an uncomfortable
place was kind of deep stuckness in my
life in its it made me feel like there
was a kind of perspective of clash and
absurdity between my scientific work and
might embodied existence but then I had
the insight that I didn't need a theory
of relevance what I actually needed was
a theory of relevance realization and
that that was deeply analogous to what
Darwin had done and then that sort of
unlocked everything for me in a really
profound way and that insight has been
sort of a touchstone for me I keep
coming back to it again and again again
that's why I got perhaps a little bit I
don't know brusque when I was talking
about ideologies right the attempt to
come up with a definition a final
account a perfect rendering of what's
relevant what's sacred what's ultimately
real to us like these are all deeply
deeply misplaced and that comes from for
me the depth I believe the depth of that
insight that we can't have a theory of
relevance but we can have a theory of
relevance realization and we therefore
need to fundamentally reorient how we
understand knowledge meaning making
wisdom sacredness etc
the next question is from the patron
Mike what is your take on the hard
problem of consciousness property
dualism epi phenomenal ISM pants
psychism so Mike that's that's a great
question I'm currently teaching a course
right now on consciousness and I take
about 18 hours of lecture to try and
answer that question because I think the
topic deserves it
I've written a paper with Anderson Todd
and Richard woo and unpublished
manuscript I think it's like 65 pages
long or something like this it's a huge
sort of Frankensteinian beast that if I
ever want to get it published I'm gonna
have to break it up into smaller
documents it's sort of circulating it's
taken on a weird life of its own
why am I saying all that I want to say
all that because I'm aware that no
matter what I say on this it's going to
be there for two brief in inadequate
because we have very limited time so I
want to give you a basic idea of how I
what my position is I think the hard
problem of consciousness which is
generated by arguments concerning the
explanatory gap which I won't review
I've talked about these in a previous
Q&A I think we we need to step back and
break up the phenomena that for which
we're finding the hard problem so the
hard problem of consciousness for many
of you who are listening is the is the
the idea that there seemed to be aspects
of consciousness that we will now not be
able to explain from a scientific
perspective at least from a
computational perspective and I take
that the problem actually breaks up into
three different problems the first
problem is sort of problems surrounding
our sense of subjectivity and our sense
of ownership and the privacy of our
consciousness and then there's the
problem of qualia and unlike many people
I break this up into two kinds of qualia
that need to be distinguished to
actually account for a lot of the Phenom
nology there are the typical ones the
prototypical ones the adjective aqualia
like the blueness of blue and the
greenness of green which doesn't seem to
be anything we can give a physical
account up but then there are also the
adverbial qualia the adverbial qualia
have to do with the way consciousness
has a hereness a noun as to either way
it's centering upon me and those are the
adverbial qualia because they have to do
more with a way of being than with a
particular a way of being conscious than
with a particular moment of content so
here's the thing I want to say I think
the adjective qualia above for which
much blood and ink is spilled in this
question of consciousness are actually
have too high of a status in the problem
what do I mean by that I think this
clear case is that the adjective of
qualia are not necessary for
consciousness this is called the pure
consciousness event many people have
experienced it I've experienced it you
are conscious you're not conscious of
anything you're not conscious even
conscious of consciousness you just have
a raw participatory
consciousness right and that says to me
that the adjective of qualia are not
necessary for consciousness and
therefore are not fundamental to its
functionality what doesn't disappear in
the pure consciousness event are the
adjective of qualia people they don't
lose hereness nowness the way things are
sort of bound together in fact they they
that become sort of extended into you
know sort of a kind of absolute here
nowness unity eternity so the at the eye
verbal qualia don't go away the
adjective of qualia remain also I think
the adjective of qualia are not
sufficient for consciousness I think if
you had consciousness and it was
completely not bound with any particular
perspective had no hereness nowness was
in no way bound in intelligibility to
anything else
no I do not think you would say that you
therefore had an instance of
consciousness that that kind of purely
atomic qualia adjective ah qualia would
not constitute consciousness okay if a
Jacobo qualia are neither necessary nor
sufficient whereas the adverbial qualia
seem to be then we can move towards
talking about how we might address the
adverbial qualia and here's where I then
would have to point to larger arguments
that I made in the series of a
consciousness I think we can give a
naturalistic explanation of these
adjective features qualia if you like in
terms of relevance realization relevance
realization gives us how things are
specialized it gives us our salience
Landscaping it gives us the hereness and
nowness and the fitted together Ness of
consciousness it gives us centrality
because things are relevant to us so it
gives us our perspective all knowing in
fact this is what I would argue that
consciousness is our participatory
knowing of and through our perspectival
knowing and that we can give an
explanation of that in terms of both its
functionality and how its generating
right consciousness the the the
experiential aspects of consciousness in
terms of relevance realization so in
that sense I think ultimately the
machinery of intelligence when properly
understood dovetails with the machinery
of consciousness and this helps me to
also explain something that many people
who talk about the hard problem have a
difficulty explaining the deep intuition
that profound often intuition people
have that the attribution of
consciousness is running is highly
correlated with the attribution of
intelligence people attribute
consciousness where they see good
evidence for sophisticated intelligence
and they have expectations
of sophisticated intelligence when they
were more willing to attribute
consciousness that sent that sense of
perspective all-knowing and centrality
given to by relevance realization also
helps to explain the the sort of the
subjectivity and the - of consciousness
so what does that make me that makes me
I mean I'm a Norman duction on a non
reductionist physicalist I do not think
you can explain all the things I just
explained like relevance realization at
the level of the ontology given to us by
physics I think that we're talking about
emergent aspects of that are carried in
real patterns and that therefore what
I'm talking about is ultimately
consistent with physics and and with
naturalism but is not reducible to it so
that's my that's my somewhat for many of
you that was probably taxing on your
patience and attention as I seem to have
gone out on about consciousness because
I I I hope you could understand that
that was in to my mind a an answer that
was radically too short to address
consciousness which is the holy grail of
cognitive science and sort of one of the
last-ditch defenses that many people
take in the broader public discourse
against naturalism another question from
the patron Rob you talked about virtues
such as courage but are there any vices
that you or think are important to avoid
in general how do you conceptualize Vice
and how does it fit into your system of
thought yeah I mean I think that first
of all I want to indicate that I think
the four cardinal virtues are ones that
should be given preeminence which are
wisdom courage justice and sovereign
which is not really well translated by
temperance or moderation this is your
ability to be basically have educated
your salience Lance
so that you are tempted towards what is
good and what is true and what is
beautiful you've--you've you sort of
doing the opposite of bullshitting your
salience landscape is been properly
trained so that you are naturally led
towards our normative ideals
that's our Sun I think therefore the
vices that we should pay attention to
are devices that are the opposite that
the lack of the cardinal virtues but I
had sort of an Aristotelian idea here
that when we talk about a vice with
respect to a virtue we're talking about
vices both of excess and vices of
deficit I think what a virtue is it is
very very very much overlapping with
what a virtual engine is it's a set of
enabling constraints that that lift you
away from vices of deficiency and then a
set a set of selective constraints that
keep you from vices of excess and
therefore they constantly help evolve
your optimal gripping on reality so that
you much better track our normative
ideals so what do I mean by that well
the classic example is of course
ourselves courage right courage courage
is not the ability to face danger all of
the virtues have an aspect of wisdom to
them courage is the ability to see
through the way your fear might be
bullshitting you about what needs to be
done or about what is really going on or
both and that's not the same thing and
once you see that you see that you can
have a vice of excess you can be
foolhardy you can just face danger you
could jump off cliffs and run into
traffic and that's not a virtue
precisely because right it's you you're
virtually in your capacity to regulate
your optimal Griffing on the world is
lopsided there's not enough selective
constraints keeping you from the vices
of excess but right the there's also the
vice of cowardice
where you let right that fear blinds you
and prevent you from doing what needs to
be done seeing how things really are and
of course those are often related so you
need an abling constraints that
literally encourage you that motivates
you that make you consider more options
that that open you up and provoke you to
explore and take a risk and take a
chance and so what you've seen of course
is that you know I'm describing vices
and virtues in terms of the same is
shaded by which I explain relevance
realization because as I as I think I'm
trying to indicate virtue I mean that
there's a virtue originally met power a
virtue is a capacity it is a way of
seeing and being that such that you see
through various kinds of illusions and
self-deceptions and you see into the
affordances of what will take you and in
us in the sense of a like a being
tempted you see through and you see into
your on fourth adduced you're drawn
forth towards what it's true and good
and beautiful so I think you know if you
think about each one of the cardinal
virtues and vices of excess and vices of
deficiency I I would recommend those as
the primary vices you attempt to avoid
this is from the patron Elmo I was
interested to hear what you thought
about the two scientific approach and if
you thought it relates to your series in
a meaningful way yeah very much that
this is you know this is something I'm
currently exploring lachman's book lost
what is it lost knowledge of the
imagination and and other books
especially some the books the book I
book I'm reading on Barfield and some
books on the early post contines
like Schlegel and others
that has put me on - oh I can't remember
the name of this author he's writing
books about you know you know this this
way of skiing that people like good to
emphasize this new way of seeing so and
I guess I'm coming to a conclusion
similar to some of these authors I'm
reading insofar as Goethe was attempting
to propose a science to challenge Newton
good - loses but I think what good - one
way of reinterpreting Goethe is that
what he's doing is indicating a new way
of seeing that recan we're seeing is
much more broadly about your whole
sensory motor loop in the way you're
coupled to the world sort of the
perspectival and participatory aspects
of knowing and that's what I want to put
my finger on I think what good is doing
is a way of seeing and being that
reconnects us to the procedural the
perspectival and the participatory and
therefore discloses aspects of ourselves
and the reality that are only disclosed
through those kinds of knowing and so I
think good does work is is very
important well to me it's the reason why
I'm hesitating is there's that work and
the work he did on the understanding the
deep understanding of symbolism these
there's an intuition in my mind that
they're deeply connected and but I I'm
not confident right now and trying to
articulate what that intuition looks
like so I apologize for my hesitancy but
there there's something going on there
right you know that that this new way of
seeing and being that reconnects us
takes us into our deepest existential
and ultimate concerns because though
those kinds of knowing are actually
appropriate the the perspectival and the
participatory especially are deeply
appropriate for our existential and
ultimate concerns
and the way you know good to try to
break out of both empiricism and
rationalism or positivism or empiricism
because those all sort of trade around
with each other
I think they yeah that's also deeply
consonant with how I'm trying to get
back to you know the transitivity that's
disclosed and prospective and
participatory knowing and I think that's
also what good to look at me I'm doing
all this grasping gesture because I'm
trying to reach for something here but I
think that's an excellent question and
that this is this is a line of thought
I'm currently pursuing in depth we have
another question from the patron the
Betterman project thank you very much I
thank you everyone of course for your
support in the art world we sometimes
speak of someone's style as a kind of
fingerprint something which though it
can resemble a genre is unique to that
individual as a trace of their skills
development those idea cook the
cognitive styles of rationality you
speak of and after the meaning crisis
episode 40 to be similar where thinkers
can fall into similar school but have
very distinct habits propensities and
lose their earned indicative of a
person's cognitive style or would we
expect cognitive styles to be less
personalistic and stylistic that is a
really good question
wolf that's a very good question
Oh what I would like a lot of time to
think about that that's an excellent
question of it like it's it's an
excellent cog side question and it's but
it has also excellent philosophical
import for the way in which rationality
you know connect what do I mean like
wrap our higher cognitive processes like
rationality are not just features of us
that we possess we identify with them
they're part of our sense of self and
and what's interesting about them and
this question points to it is you know
rationality that's the question that's
the feature being mentioned here I'm not
claiming its exclusive please but that's
the that's the feature here our
rationality we think of it sign what
simultaneously is something that
gives us our identity as persons and
moral agents and human beings but we
also think it's bound up with that
particular kind of entity we call
ourself and the way in which we make
sense of things that is a really really
good question and I think the answer is
that that you know there are that in
addition to sort of you know the the the
you know the the basic s1 s2 distinction
you know where s1 is very bottom-up and
self organizing and s2 is very top-down
and and linear I think we can talk about
a lot more specificity that kind of more
individual style that indeed that would
be expressed in how people are
addressing their see part of what
rationality and character and this is in
wrist at an idea right is your character
your carrot you cultivate your character
not just to aspire to what is good which
we all should do generically but also
idiosyncratically to compensate for your
own personal proclivities and tendencies
towards vice or deficiency right so how
so if you know if I'm tending to because
of my background in my Constitution
towards being a coward the way in which
I need to be more rational is I need I
need a style that emphasizes a lot of
practices that enhance my ability to see
through the self you know there are
universal ways in which human beings are
pursuing rationality and have particular
cognitive a cognitive styles around that
yeah there's going to be there's gonna
be very specific ways in which people
are cultivating their rational character
their ability to reason etc that are
going to be idiosyncratically reflective
and this of course this of course yeah
this makes sense because this was
Aristotle's idea right that the the
virtue is always relative to the
individual and of course for Aristotle
who has a developmental perspective
relative to the development of the
individual and also to their context
that doesn't mean the virtues are
relative it's this is not a form of
relativism it's it has to do with what I
just talked about that me being virtuous
in how I'm making sense is going to have
some idiosyncratic specific features
because of my personal Constitution my
personal past and my personal course of
development thank you that was an
excellent question I really appreciate
that question a lot really made me think
very deeply here's another question from
patron Dan thank you again Dan what role
does latency mismatch play and relevance
realization and are there any wisdom
practices for slow agents adapting to a
fast pace arena so latency mismatch is
let me let me give you an example this
comes out of a conversation I actually
had with Dan and so I appreciate this
and I want to give him credit but let's
say let's talk about the degree to which
temporal relevance and timing actually
matter to your cognition something that
Pascal pointed out a long time ago when
he talked about the spirit of finesse as
opposed to the spirit of geometry so for
example that's something that has to do
more with sort of neurological
biological limitations right you know on
how fast you can sort of process thing
imagine that you were to take one of my
lectures and play it on you know triple
speed three times as fast as it normally
is it would be very very hard let's say
I we get it so you can still hear every
word but the the pausing and I mean I
know my lectures are already quite dense
so they would get super dense they would
get temporally super dense and probably
become impenetrable to to you because
the speed at which your sensory-motor
loop is looping has a certain timing to
it and Dan is pointing to the fact that
people have differences in this looping
I think he's also alluding to the fact
that our the way we're cyborgs and a
mess with technology right we're
exposing ourselves to environments in
which that tempo of things is speeding
up and Han talks about this wonderfully
in his book the scent of time and how
we're losing the ability to linger and
to and to experience the duration of
things the unfolding of things the
development of things talked about this
earlier if you remember with you know
the the the the the the death of melody
within popular music and things like
that and so there's two things here
there's two recommendations first the
one that Han made is we need to remember
to stop and to move to aspects of
reality that are more in comportment
with our our for lack of a better term
our natural you know temporal latency
and our sensory motor loop and you know
in things like how fast our working
memory refreshes and all kinds of things
like that which I won't go into
technical detail so I think that you
could make a good case with that what
Han is saying is that this is a shift in
our existential mode we move into a
spirit of finesse we open up our
experiencing time so that timing and
lingering and the unfoldment of things
is what we're carrying more about rather
than again getting towards specific goal
states and that that will help with
remembering the being mode and help with
alleviate the kind of modal confusions
that I think Han is talking about in
lots of his criticisms of you know in
the burnout Society the trend the
transparency of society and the agony of
arrows but Dan is also making a
recommendation of well but can we also
help speed people up so that they don't
become you know
and I want a term that indicates a class
of people that are sort of pushed away
you know maybe like presents or
something you know that we don't want
people that loo that fall behind in the
ability to couple to the Technosphere
and if they can't couple to the
Technosphere because of the rapidity all
right of the way of its turnover if it's
of its timing right that the latency
that Dan is talking about the relevance
realization machinery can't couple to it
that they are going to be excluded and
they're going to be excluded from where
the culture is moving the culture is no
longer meeting in the town square or the
church or even in right you know the
univer the town in the university or the
market even the marketplace that you
know where the culture is meeting here
this is where the culture is meeting and
it's meeting increasingly within hyper
technology so if we don't address how to
help people with that then of course
they are going to be excluded from the
culture as a process of meaning making
and as a locus of influence and power
which i think is the deep import of
Dan's question now that's a tricky thing
because basically what we need to then
think about and I think this is an
important recommendation is that in our
ecology of practices and I talked about
this in terms of kinds of practices we
need practices that are designed as
transitional practices that are helped
designed to get people right more
appropriately connected obviously
they're going to need to train a lot of
the self-deceptive machine a lot of the
machinery for overcoming self-deception
because of the way in which the
Technosphere in this social media sphere
and all those things are just awash in
so much I mean literally the
we're doing things already beyond our
understanding because of the way in
which the technology and the systems are
getting taking taking on a life of their
own and running away from us so we need
to especially train people in that we
need to train people to increase the the
timing and their finesse for this world
and that would that we need somebody who
it would be good at sort of to teaching
people you know what's your consent
mahai talks about about how to get the
right kind of feedback the right kind of
coupling and to break things up and
chunk the tasks in such a way that it's
possible to start getting in the flow
state with respect to interacting with
this arena in a powerful way and I don't
know what that looks like specifically I
mean this is something where I'd have to
defer to other people's expertise I
could talk about you know what cognition
can do as a cognitive scientist and I've
invoked some of those processes but what
the specific pedagogical tools that
would be needed in order to get people
into a fan of flowing finesse with the
techno sphere that's that's something I
think that's going to require collective
intelligence and a network of relevant
expertise but thank you for that very
very very good question thank you to
patron subscribers and everyone watching
right now as always your support is
really crucial to continuing to produce
these videos and for supporting the
science we're doing to find solutions to
the main crisis so a reminder about
after Socrates but I have an
announcement to make about after
Socrates and so this is important I've
decided for a couple of reasons that I'm
actually going to postpone the release
of after Socrates to the end of July
throughout one of my primary reasons for
doing this is that there are some fun
any opportunities that have emerged and
and that would help me with fund the
production of the series and therefore
I'm going to pursue these funding
opportunities so that's sort of an
economic and logistical reason the
second reason is that I that this
project is becoming profound for me I'm
just getting deeper and deeper into it
just doing some really important work
with Christopher master Pietro and Peter
Lindbergh and others and the dialogues
I'm having with guys and sonic and
Jordan Hall etc the work you know with
rebel wisdom so well I want to continue
that research and I also want to
continue these discussions which brings
me to some good news there's going to be
two new series that are going to be
starting very soon gonna be released
very soon one is going to be it's yet to
be named but basically it's going to be
more of these discussions more of these
Socratic dialogues with people and the
basic theme is what the spirituality
mean for us now in our you know what's
the relationship between spirituality
and science and spirituality in the
meaning crisis and spirituality as and
you know the the this changed this
radical change that we're facing and
what you know the hyper technology and
what Thomas Bjorkman calls the meta
crisis so that's and I have already
filmed several of these discussions and
so that's that they're going to be
released regularly on the Friday slot
I'm also starting to film tomorrow a new
series with Anderson Todd that some of
you have met and also Leo Ferraro who
have mentioned is co-author with mine
you might have seen him on some videos
with guys hence talk
it's minding media the idea there is to
try to try to bring some of these ideas
that can be very often abstract and
difficult for people into a more
accessible arena of discussion
by looking for these philosophical
topics these cognitive science topics
within various movies like for example I
recently wrote a letter wiki exchange
with David David Chapman about Joker and
how you we might see a shift from the
zombie myth to a kind of really nasty
narcissism and what that might mean or
you know thinking about arrival and the
interesting questions it poses about the
relationship between language and
cognition and human identity in time so
this is the kind of thing we're gonna do
we're gonna take a look at movies
I'll give sort of a like a 15 minute
mini-lecture bring up some questions and
then they'll be around how you know just
continual round house discussion between
Leo and Anderson I about trying to get
some deeper understanding of our meaning
making processes and our aspirations
towards wisdom and spirituality and
depth by taking an in-depth look at some
of these very thought-provoking movies
so that's all coming out one more thing
there's there's currently an IndieGoGo
campaign for a book that I'm working on
with Daniel Craig called the cognitive
continuum this is a book there's two
videos out there that give you a short
one and if you just want a quick idea a
long one that which Daniel and I have a
long discussion the cognitive continuum
is this idea it's a it's a line of
argumentation that went through after
the awakening for the meaning crisis
story and that's this idea that there's
a continuum between the processes of
insight flow mystical experience
transform higher states of consciousness
transformative experiences and
enlightenment and trying to work that
out and so I want to state again clearly
I do not get any income from this
IndieGoGo campaign
nor will I get any income from this book
the point of raising the funding is to
help Daniel who is not a university
professor but a you know a student to
help you know fund him so that he can
devote the time to partner with me in
the writing of this book he's also
taking a lot of extra tasks that need
funding about putting together the
artwork etc so please consider
supporting that IndieGoGo campaign okay
we're going to shift to some live
questions now from the chat and this is
from the patreon the golden thread could
third order attention ality and
imitation be necessary acceptations for
psycho texts like language numeracy etc
is so with the nature function of
mimesis become fundamental for cognitive
science I think so this did this is
tricky because it there's an issue where
we might want to think you know I think
I've sucked acceptation of course is is
very important but the imitate I mean
the imitation is very necessary very
much for internalizing other people's
perspectives and giving us sort of
second-order cognition like I like I
argued in the series I'm trying I think
that mimesis the ability to imitate
other theories again another reason why
I'm hesitating is because I'm sort of
doing work right now with Dan Hsia Pia
and connected to the after Socrates
project about you know the sense of we
agency where people when they're in
groups like encircling they go from you
know I and you to we and then and
there's all but there's even a sense of
sort of a third factor above and beyond
all the individual participants and how
this relates to mimesis is what you see
is that there there's stuff happening in
things like circling in which people
they're there there's a pole there's
something like a point of processing a
self-organizing process in which people
move between mimicry and and in that
mimicry they're trying to get sort of
what Durkheim called the mechanical
solidarity which people are sort of
behaving very much in the same way and
the mimesis is of course therefore
crucial to engendering that aspect of
collective distributed cognition but but
that is counterbalanced by people doing
something else where they enter into
complementarity where they're not
mimicking but they're doing something
that complements that's different from
what sort of like for example of you you
and I are are dancing think about the
interplay between mimicry in which we're
doing the same thing and complementarity
where I'm actually doing might be doing
the opposite thing you're stepping
forward and I'm stepping back for
example and what you see is people are
constantly fluently moving between these
poles in which they are bound by a kind
of mechanical solidarity and then
they're bound by a deep interdependence
because each part on its own can't do
the function like if you're lifting a
table and one person has to be walking
backwards another person has to be
walking forward and so there's this
constant shift going on there so that's
why I was hesitating when I was talking
about
mimesis I think mimesis is very
important as I argued for internalizing
a lot of important psycho tech but I
think when we're going to move to psycho
tech of dialectic with a psycho psycho
tech that helps to engender and enhance
deal logos that I talked about earlier
then we need we're going to need to
think about mimesis and complementarity
as forming a much more sophisticated
opponent processing for how collective
intelligence is operating within
distribu
cognition and you can see why this is
really important when trying to
understand how we can get to do logos so
I hope that was helpful question I
really want to get to this next question
because I David sweat Lowe is a very
good patron and he he he often
participates in the watch parties that
future thinker make about about my my
videos from awakening for the meeting
crisis and he often has very insightful
things to say here's this question
participatory knowing seems the hardest
lens to pull away and look at rather
than look through but this seems
essential perhaps shamanic practices do
this thoughts or clarifications on this
yeah I think that's it that's cool so
let's try and work at what what's
participatory knowing again
participatory knowing is at the deepest
levels right at the level of the
fundamental framing the way in which
you're coupled to the world so that the
agent arena Co forum in a transgender
man er right and so a way of thinking
about this Chris and I just did this in
the chapter that we're writing for we're
hoping will come out in the meta modern
anthology on Socratic dialogue and deal
logos about this idea about a
participatory knowing and the the idea
of the mutual shaping for example an
organism in its environment by its
evolutionary heritage so that
affordances open up between them so for
example because of my evolutionary
heritage right I like I can be shaped to
certain kinds of objects right there's
an affordance of grass for ability where
of course it's not graspable
to a dragon dragonfly I'm at least not
in the liftable sense of gospel and so